SEAN P. ALVAREZ

Woburn, MA 01801 | <u>alvie0818@gmail.com</u> www.linkedin.com/in/seanpalvarez

PROFILE: SENIOR SOFTWARE ARCHITECT

Senior software development architect and technology professional with 10+ years of experience leading cutting-edge IT initiatives, projects, and teams in the design, development, implementation, production, support, and enhancement of complex web-based and enterprise applications.

- Apply a full understanding of all phases of the software development life cycle, current development techniques, methodologies (Agile Scrum, Waterfall), and tools to gather and translate user requirements into solutions that meet evolving business needs and objectives.
- Analyze and drive key platform decisions, software development, and technology selections to design and enhance product standards and further product technologies.
- Plan, organize, direct, control, and evaluate the information systems operations, projects, and staff, working collaboratively across all levels to evaluate and plan system requirements, specifications, budgets, and strategy.
- Lead and contribute to IT operational excellence strategy through the implementation of organizational improvements, training, and IT infrastructure solutions.

SKILLS & CAPABILITIES

- Over 8 years of experience in the development, building, enhancement, and maintenance of key system features and production software systems across all application tiers.
- Natural leadership ability coupled with a strong technical acumen, knowledge of all phases of the SDLC, and experience delivering projects in an agile environment.
- Experience developing cloud software services combined with a full understanding of design for scalability, performance, and reliability.
- Demonstrated expertise in establishing architectural principles, designs, prototype technology, and technical feasibility.
- Proven ability to motivate, mentor, and build cohesive teams focused on maintaining architectural vision and software quality.
- Certifications in CompTIA A++, Network +, and MCTS: HTML, CSS and JavaScript.
- Technical competencies include mastery of multiple software development tools, and extensive experience with C#, Java, C, C++, HTML, SQL, LINQ, EF, CSS, JavaScript, VBA, UML languages and open source technologies.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Endurance Services Ltd., Woburn, MA SENIOR SOFTWARE ARCHITECT

April 2012 - Present

Provide leadership and oversight of application and software system development and support standards, infrastructure, tools, projects, and teams. Utilize sound and disciplined development practices and standards to direct the full SDLC for architecture design, build, and maintenance of web-based enterprise applications for a global organization. Work directly within the PMO to lead in the planning and execution of application department functions and projects.

- Recruited as a programmer and evolved to a leadership role to oversee the programming, development, and implementation of the application stack for a newly launched business extension for the company (Blue Capital).
 - Migrated manual project and process-tracking data models to database-backed and IT-managed web applications with no business disruption or data loss.
 - Delivered a suite of web-based applications and architected the responsive applications for future use and expansion initiatives (using modern C#, JavaScript, HTML, and SQL Server).
 - Developed the solution from the ground up; met aggressive requirements gathering and prototype and solution delivery requirements enabling the crucial, on-time NYSE launch of the new entity.
- Brought in to salvage a failing project at risk of not meeting project deliverables. Assumed a leadership role in the project; re-architected major components of the application to deliver a scalable solution to meet production and QA requirements. Completed project 4 weeks ahead of estimated delivery date.

- Led multiple projects to migrate mission-critical applications and sync processes. Improved application security, stability, and maintainability through the migration to .NET 4.5 with WCF/WEBAPI/REST services, SQL Server 2008 R2. Added on-demand sync between SQL Server and SAP with BizTalk 2010.
- Collaborated with London-based business unit to eliminate an internally-developed line of business application with a 3rd party solution to enhance integration with the Lloyd's of London marketplace. Migrated all data without any data loss or business disruption.
- Secured Pluralsight licenses to enhance team performance through continuous training and development.

ForensicSoft Inc., Providence, RI LEAD TECHNOLOGIST

January 2007 - August 2012

Hired to leverage technology expertise to lead in the development and implementation of all aspects of IT infrastructure, management, and oversight as well as product development and deployment. Managed all aspects of IT procurement, licensing, 3rd party vendor and contract management, website maintenance, and technical support.

- Wrote the code for the company's signature products: SAFE Windows Boot Disk and SAFE Block.
 - Developed software from the ground up utilizing front-end application and windows driver that evolved with each new Windows operating system release.
 - o Managed all aspects of product testing, licensing, and integration with 3rd party applications.
 - Worked collaboratively with the US Department of Defense to have the product formally tested and verified by the NIJ to prove the product's validity, stability, and use within the court system.
 - o Led the deployment of the cloud-based solution to the corporate website.
- Established and maintained encryption standards for the company for all IT-related transactions and functions.
- Supervised staff of interns and contractors in all aspects of product development, testing, and deployment.

University of Rhode Island, Kingston, RI SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT MANAGER - Digital Forensics Center

December 2007 - April 2012

Responsible for the research and development of new software and digital forensic techniques to advance technology in the field of digital forensics investigations, research, and education as well as securing research grants for the university.

- Taught courses on FAT, FAT32, and NTFS file systems and partition structures to 60+ students over 3 semesters. Developed training videos and all course related materials.
- Created an automated image scanner (RedLight) for use by law enforcement to detect child pornography on suspect computers. The application was at the forefront of human image detection, serving as the foundation for Master's thesis and secured a significant grant for the university.

Rhode Island State Police Computer Crimes Unit, Providence, RI STUDENT INTERN

June 2007 - December 2007

Assisted with and observed processes related to the investigation of computer criminal investigations. Created GREP strings for use with forensic software (EnCase); wiped and prepared drives and computers for use in imaging.

Microsystems Integration, Inc., Pawcatuck, CT SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT INTERN

June 2006 - January 2007

Excelled in utilizing standard and distributed software architecture to develop systems integration products for the U.S. Coast Guard.

Leslie's Pool Supply Corp., Weymouth, MA STORE MANAGER

April 2000 - June 2006

Managed all aspects of day-to-day store operations with responsibility for the planning and execution of sales strategy, merchandising, inventory control, vendor management, reporting, customer service, and staff scheduling.

- Credited with increasing sales by 38% by demonstrating strong sales acumen, customer service, and motivating staff to go above and beyond expectations.
- Trained and promoted 3 employees from assistant to store manager.

EDUCATION

University of Rhode Island, Kingston, RI Master of Science, Computer Science | Masters Certificate, Digital Forensics

University of Rhode Island, Kingston, RI Bachelor of Science, Computer Science (Math & Digital Forensics Minors)